Guide to the Charles A. Lindbergh Photographs Collection 1927-1977
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Charles A. Lindbergh photographs collection
1927-1977
1927-1933
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Org. Lot 743
0.36 cubic feet 80 photographs in 1 document box
Many images in this collection document the visit to Portland by famed aviator Charles Lindbergh on Sept. 14, 1927. Other images include America First rallies, family appearances, other airplanes owned by Lindbergh, and memorabilia.
Biographical Note
Charles A. Lindbergh (1902-1974) learned to fly in 1922 and became famous five years later when he made the first solo non-stop flight across the Atlantic Ocean May 20-21, 1927. In July of that year, he began a flying tour of the United States under the sponsorship of the Daniel Guggenheim Fund. He reached Portland, Or., Sept. 14, 1927, landing on Swan Island. Two days later he left for San Francisco.
In 1932, Lindbergh again made headlines when his son was kidnapped and killed. The media attention during the investigation and trial convinced Lindbergh and his wife, Anne Morrow Lindbergh, to move to Europe for several years. Returning in 1939, Charles Lindbergh became active in the America First movement opposing U.S. participation in World War II. The movement disbanded after the attack on Pearl Harbor in 1941. During World War II, he worked with the Ford Motor Company to convert automobile plants to airplane production. In 1944 he flew many combat missions in the Pacific war, although he was a civilian.
After the war ended, Lindbergh retired from public life to write and work as a technical advisor in the airline industry. In the 1960s he became active in the conservation movement. He died in 1974.
The bulk of the images in this collection document Charles Lindbergh's 1927 visit to Portland, Or. on his flying tour of the United States. Subjects depicted include his landing on Swan Island and meetings with Portland mayor George L. Baker and Oregon governor Issac Patterson. The remainder of the collection consists of images related to Lindbergh's later life as a political and conservation activist and airplane pioneer, including photographs of Lindberg's airplanes (including the Spirit of St. Louis), portraits of Lindberg with prominent politicians such as Tom McCall photographs, and other portraits of various members of the Linberg family. Both amateur snapshots and newspaper photographs are represented; photographers include Gardiner P. Bissell, Harris & Ewing, and photographers for the Oregonian and Oregon Journal newspapers.
The nine folders of the collection are arranged in four series:
Series A: Portland visit, Sept. 14-15, 1927
Series B: Charles Lindbergh's airplanes, 1927-1931
Series C: Portraits, 1927-1977
Series D: Other images, 1927-1977
The collection is open to the public.
Includes Library accession nos. 7466 and 18997.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Baker, George L. (George Luis), 1868-1941--Photographs.; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974--Photographs.; Lindbergh, Anne Morrow, 1906-2001--Photographs.; McCall, Tom, 1913 - --Photographs.; Patterson, Isaac Lee, 1859-1929--Photographs.; Bissell, Gardiner P.--Photographs.
Lindberg family--Photographs.
Spirit of St. Louis (Airplane)--Photographs.; Harris & Ewing; Oregon Journal (Firm); Oregonian (Firm)
Swan Island Industrial Park (Or.)--Photographs.
Aeronautics--Photographs.; Air pilots--Photographs.; Airplanes--Photographs.
Oregon; Portland; Photographs; Transportation
Photographic prints.
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Portland Visit, Sept. 14-15, 1927; Series A; 35 images
  Includes scenes of Charles Lindbergh landing on Swan Island, and with various dignitaries, including Mayor George L. Baker and Governor Isaac Patterson, as well as riding in a parade and speaking.
  - Lindbergh's reception, 1927 Sept. 14 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Includes images of Lindbergh on Swan Island and being escorted into Portland and with Mayor George L. Baker, Gov. Isaac L. Patterson, Rose Festival Queen Dorothy Mielke, and Julius Meier.
  - Parade, 1927 Sept. 15 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Includes images of Lindbergh with Mayor George L. Baker.
  - Lindbergh speaking, 1927 Sept. 15 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Charles Lindbergh's airplanes, 1927-1931; Series B; 22 images
  - Charles Lindbergh and the Spirit of St. Louis, 1927; 1928; undated (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Spirit of St. Louis and other Lindbergh airplanes, 1927; 1928; 1929; 1931 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Portraits, 1927-1977; Series C; 26 images
  - Charles Lindbergh with others, 1927-1973 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Sen. Burton K. Wheeler, 1940
    - John Cudahy, U.S. Ambassador to Belgium, 1940
    - Sen. Henry M. Jackson, 1970
    - Mayor James Rolph, Jr., San Francisco, 1927
    - Gov. Tom McCall, Oregon, 1971
    - Frank Borman, astronaut, 1971
    - Anne Morrow Lindbergh, 1929; 1930; 1933; 1941
    - Jack Maddux, 1933
    - Sen. and Mrs. D. Worth Clark, 1941
    - Kathleen Norris, 1941
    - Lillian Gish, 1941
  - Lindbergh family, 1929-1977 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Anne Morrow Lindbergh, 1929; 1968; 1977
    - Jon M. Lindbergh, 1963; 1970; 1974
    - Reeve Lindbergh Brown, 1977
  - Other identified portraits, 1928-1930 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Marshall Headle, 1930
    - M.A. Mankey, 1928
    - Tex Rankin, 1928
- Other images, 1927-1977; Series D; 3 images
  - Other images, 1927-1977 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Swan Island field prepared for Lindbergh landing (image reversed), 1927
    - Aero Club of Oregon honorary membership certificate, 1927
    - Commemorative medal, 50th anniversary of Lindbergh's flight, 1977